Guide to the Anne Tyler Papers, 1958-2016 RL.01318
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Anne Tyler papers
1958-2016
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Tyler, Anne
RL.01318
29 Linear Feet
Pulitzer Prize winning author of The Accidental Tourist, Breathing Lessons, Celestial Navigation, Ladder of Years, and other popular novels. Collection includes manuscript drafts, printed material, holograph manuscripts and typescripts of Tyler's novels and short stories, including Dinner at the Homesick Restaurant; clippings of articles about Tyler and her writings; serials containing articles by or about Tyler and her work; correspondence between Tyler and her publishers; and materials regarding adaptations of her novels, including the movie The Accidental Tourist. Later additions include holograph manuscripts of A Patchwork Planet and Noah's Compass; an advance uncorrected proof of Back When We Were Grownups (2001); drafts for Digging to America, The Amateur Marriage, Back When We Were Grownups, The Beginner's Goodbye, A Blue Spool of Thread, Vinegar Girl, and Clock Dance; correspondence between Tyler and her editors and agents; publicity materials; some Tyler family correspondence; book reviews; and book covers.
8300 Items
Access Restrictions
A portion of the collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Anne Tyler Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift between 1989-2019.
Biographical Note
Anne Tyler (b. 1941) is an award-winning author, born in Minneapolis, Minn. She spent her youth in and near Raleigh, N.C.. She graduated from Duke University and completed graduate work in Russian studies at Columbia University. In 1963, Tyler married Taghi Modarressi. In the following year, they moved to Montreal, Canada, where Tyler wrote and worked in the McGill University Law Library. The couple had two daughters. During this time, Tyler began working with editor Judith Jones of Alfred A. Knopf publishing house. In 1967, the family settled in Baltimore, and Tyler sets most of her novels there.
Tyler has published novels, short stories, and children's books. Her novels include If Morning Ever Comes, The Tin Can Tree, A Slipping-Down Life, Celestial Navigation, Searching for Caleb, Earthly Possessions, Morgan's Passing, Dinner at the Homesick Restaurant, The Accidental Tourist, Breathing Lessons, Saint Maybe, Ladder of Years, A Patchwork Planet, Back When We Were Grownups, The Amateur Marriage, Digging to America, Noah's Compass, and The Beginner's Goodbye. She has collaborated with her daughter Mitra, an illustrator, on two children's books: Tumble Tower and Timothy Tugbottom Says No!.
Tyler has received recognition for many of her literary works. Among her awards are the National Book Critics Circle Award, received in 1985 for The Accidental Tourist, and the Pulitzer Prize for Fiction, received in 1989 for Breathing Lessons.
Chronology List of Anne Tyler's Novels and Children's Books
1961 I Know You, Rider (unpublished)
1964 If Morning Ever Comes
1965 The Tin Can Tree
1966 Winter Birds, Winter Apples (unpublished)
1970 A Slipping-Down Life
1972 The Clock Winder
1974 Celestial Navigation
1975 Searching for Caleb
1977 Earthly Possessions
~1978-1979 Pantaleo (unpublished)
1980 Morgan's Passing
1982 Dinner at the Homesick Restaurant
1985 The Accidental Tourist
1988 Breathing Lessons
1991 Saint Maybe
1995 Ladder of Years
1993 Tumble Tower (children's book)
1998 A Patchwork Planet
2001 Back When We Were Grownups
2004 The Amateur Marriage
2005 Timothy Tugbottom Says No! (children's book)
2006 Digging to America
2010 Noah's Compass
2012 The Beginner's Goodbye
Sources:
Robert Wayne Croft, An Anne Tyler Companion (Westport, Conn.: Greenwood, 1998), 2-3.
R. Baird Shuman, Great American Writers: Twentieth Century (New York: Marshall Cavendish, 2002), 1543-5.
Collection Overview
The collection includes manuscript drafts, printed material, holograph manuscripts and typescripts of Tyler's novels and short stories; clippings of articles about Tyler and her writings; serials containing articles by or about Tyler and her work; Tyler's work-related and personal correspondence; and clipping and other materials regarding adaptations of her works, including the movie The Accidental Tourist. Later additions include holograph manuscripts of A Patchwork Planet and Noah's Compass; an advance uncorrected proof of Back When We Were Grownups (2001); drafts for Digging to America, The Amateur Marriage, Back When We Were Grownups, The Beginner's Goodbye, A Blue Spool of Thread, Vinegar Girl, and Clock Dance; correspondence between Tyler and her editors and agents; publicity materials; some Tyler family correspondence; book reviews; and book covers.
The Writings series contains novels, short stories, essays, and book reviews written by Tyler. The novels are all in draft form, with the exception of one advance uncorrected proof. Arranged in folders by date of publication, the Novels subseries includes drafts of all novels Tyler wrote between 1961 and 2016. Most of Tyler's initial drafts are handwritten, as are all of the editing marks. She also made notes for herself regarding the characters and locations in her novels. Her notes include character details and hand-drawn house floorplans. This subseries gives insight into Tyler's writing and editing process. The Short Stories & Other Writings subseries includes published and unpublished short stories, clippings, and a booklet of student essays from Tyler's time at Duke University. Oversize writings can be found in the Miscellaneous & Oversize Materials series.
The Correspondence series contains letters received or written by Anne Tyler, though the majority of the correspondence was written to Tyler. She received mail from a wide range of people, including reporters, fans, friends, publishers, editors, and event coordinators. The majority of series is arranged chronologically and provides insight into the relationships that Tyler built due to her writing, and the friendships forged through continued correspondence. One folder in this series is restricted.
The Printed Materials series contains a wide variety of materials related to Tyler and her writings. A substantial portion of this series is comprised of clippings from newspapers and magazines. Either Tyler herself or a friend or colleague subscribed to a clipping service; many book review and publicity clippings were clipped by Durrant's, an international clipping service. This series also contains materials from Eudora Welty and Tyler's speaking engagement at Duke University in 1982. This was one of the few public appearances that Tyler has made. She does not generally give interviews or go on book tours. Oversize jacket art and publicity materials can be found in the Miscellaneous & Oversize Materials series.
This collection is processed and has some restrictions. Please contact Research Services prior to coming to Special Collections to use this material.
Related Material
The David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library has many books written or edited by Anne Tyler, including foreign language editions.
Books -- Reviews; Authors and publishers -- Correspondence; Authors, American -- 20th century; American literature -- Maryland; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence; Women authors -- 20th century; Tyler, Anne -- Dinner at the Homesick Restaurant; Tyler, Anne -- Digging to America; Tyler, Anne -- Back when we were grownups; Tyler, Anne -- A patchwork planet; Tyler, Anne; Tyler, Anne -- The beginner's goodbye; Tyler, Anne -- The amateur marriage; Tyler, Anne -- The accidental tourist; Tyler, Anne -- Noah's compass; Tyler, Anne -- A spool of blue thread; Tyler, Anne -- Vinegar girl
- Writings, 1958-2016, 16 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains drafts of published and unpublished novels, short stories, and other writings.
  - Novels
    This subseries contains drafts of Tyler's published and unpublished novels. Many drafts have numbered pages. Most drafts are handwritten, but some are typed. The majority of the holographs and typescripts were edited by hand, though some materials in this subseries show no editing marks. Many notes that Tyler made for herself are included. All of her notes, including maps and floorplans, are handwritten/hand-drawn unless otherwise noted. The materials are arranged chronologically by publication date. For the unpublished novels, estimated date of completion was used.
    Notes about the materials:
    A section of I Know You, Rider part II was typed on scrap paper.
    Celestial Navigation notes include a drawing of a row house façade and the house floorplan, a chapter outline, a character list with descriptions, and a chronology and ages of characters.
    Searching for Caleb notes include alternate titles for the book, chronology, a family tree, and a street layout.
    Morgan's Passing notes include chronology and character dates as well as a house floorplan. The editing notes are photocopied slips of paper with typed questions regarding continuity of the novel, details, etc. Most notes are followed by the relevant typed page of the novel, with changes made to answer the question.
    Dinner at the Homesick Restaurant notes include a chronology of characters. An author's note on the cover page of the typescript indicates that it is the second rough typed manuscript. Years and minutes are recorded on the first page of most chapters. Times are recorded on the back of the last page of each chapter.
    Saint Maybe notes include: 4 notecards of chronology, characters, and important dates; a photocopy of pages 344-345 of The Collected Stories of André Maurois; a page of handwritten questions from editor Judith Jones; a brief letter from Tyler to Jones; and typed pages of responses to Jones's questions.
    Ladder of Years notes folder includes 14 sleeved notecards: chronology, grocery list, job ad clipping, birth chronology, Dr. Felson's house floorplan, weather notes, characters as of April 1992, lines of text, Miller house floorplan, street map, boarding house floorplan, Mapo Dofu recipe with a table seating chart on the reverse, possible chronology notes, and "OC-Balto" notes. The folder also includes: a street map with important locations marked; a printed map of Cambridge and Salisbury, MD and the surrounding area; and a photocopy of a page of American Album: Rare Photographs Collected by the Editors of American Heritage, showing pictures of C. R. Savage.
    The Amateur Marriage notecards (5 total) include two road maps with locations, Michael's Apartment floorplan, House in Elmview Acres floorplan, and St. Cassian House floorplan.
    - I Know You, Rider (Box 1)
      - Typescript, parts I-III, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - If Morning Ever Comes
      - Holograph, chapters 1-16, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - The Tin Can Tree
      - Holograph, chapters 1-15, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Winter Birds, Winter Apples
      - Holograph, chapters 1-17, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - A Slipping-Down Life (Box 2)
      - Holograph/typescript, chapters 1-5 (Box 2)
      - Holograph, chapters 6-17, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - The Clock Winder
      - Holograph, chapters 1-13, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Celestial Navigation
      - Holograph, notes & chapters 1-3 (Box 2)
      - Holograph/typescript, chapters 4-6 (Box 2)
      - Typescript, chapters 7-10 (Box 2)
    - Searching for Caleb (Box 3)
      - Holograph notes & typescript chapters 1-21, 5 folders (Box 3)
      - Related clipping (Box 3)
    - Earthly Possessions
      - Holograph, chapters 1-16, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - Related clippings (Box 3)
    - Pantaleo
      - Holograph, chapters 1-20, 23-34, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - Typescript, chapters 1-10, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Pantaleo (Box 4)
      - Typescript, chapters 11-24, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Correction sheets (Box 4)
    - Morgan's Passing
      - Holograph, notes & parts 1-6, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Holograph/typescript, parts 7-10, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Typescript, parts 1-10, 5 folders (Box 4)
      - Editing notes (Box 4)
      - Related clippings (Box 4)
    - Dinner at the Homesick Restaurant (Box 5)
      - First draft holograph, notes & chapters 1-10, 5 folders (Box 5)
      - Second draft holograph, chapters 1-10, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Typescript, chapters 1-10, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Final typescript, chapters 1-6, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Dinner at the Homesick Restaurant (Box 6)
      - Final typescript, chapter 7, earlier draft of chapter 7, revised chapter 7, chapters 8-10, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - The Accidental Tourist
      - Holograph, chapters 1-20, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Breathing Lessons
      - Holograph, parts 1-3, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Holograph, second draft parts 1-3, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Saint Maybe
      - Notes & holograph, chapters 1-2, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Saint Maybe (Box 7)
      - Holograph, chapters 3-6 & 8-10, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Holograph, second draft, chapters 1-10, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Typescript, chapters 1-10, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Ladder of Years
      - Notes (Box 7)
      - Holograph, early draft, chapters 1-4, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Ladder of Years (Box 8)
      - Holograph, early draft, chapters 5-20, 9 folders (Box 8)
      - Holograph, later draft, chapters 1-20, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Ladder of Years (Box 9)
      - Typescript, chapters 1-20, 4 folders (Box 9)
    - A Patchwork Planet
      - First draft holograph, chapters 1-14, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Second draft holograph, chapters 1-15, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Related materials (Box 9)
    - Back When We Were Grownups
      - Holograph, rough drafts, chapters 1-8 & revised chapters 5-6, 5 folders (Box 9)
    - Back When We Were Grownups (Box 10)
      - Holograph, rough draft, chapters 9-10 (Box 10)
      - Holograph, second draft, chapters 1-11, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Advance uncorrected proof (Box 10)
    - The Amateur Marriage
      - Notecards (Box 10)
      - Holograph, rough draft, chapters 1-10, 5 folders (Box 10)
      - Holograph, second draft, chapters 1-10, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Digging to America (Box 11)
      - Holograph, rough draft, chapters 1-10, 5 folders (Box 11)
      - Holograph, second draft, chapters 1-10, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Noah's Compass
      - Holograph, chapters 1-13, 4 folders (Box 11)
    - Noah's Compass (Box 12)
      - Holograph, second draft, chapters 1-13, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Noah's Compass Japanese print edition, 2011 (Box 29)
    - The Beginner's Goodbye (Box 26)
      - Holograph, rough draft, chapters 1-9, 3 folders (Box 26)
      - Holograph, second draft, chapters 1-9, 1 folder (Box 26)
    - A Spool of Blue Thread (Box 27, Box 28)
      - Holograph, rough draft, Part One, chapters 1-10, 11, 14 (Box 27)
      - Holograph, second draft, Part One, chapters 1-10, 11, 14 (Box 28)
    - Vinegar Girl
      - Holograph rough draft, chapters 1-11, 3 folders (Box 29)
      - Holograph second draft, chapters 1-11 and epilogue, 2 folders (Box 29)
    - Clock Dance
      - Holograph draft, 6 folders (Box 30)
  - Short Stories & Other Writings
    This subseries contains published and unpublished short stories written by Tyler. The stories are arranged in alphabetical order according to title.
    Also included are other writings by Tyler, such as essays on writing, clippings of book reviews she wrote, and an essay written during her Freshman English course at Duke University. An additional essay by Tyler can be found in the Miscellaneous & Oversize Materials series.
    - Stories A-I, 5 folders (Box 12)
    - Stories J-Y, 5 folders (Box 13)
    - Other writings (Box 13)
- Correspondence, 1964-1999, 2.5 boxes
  This series contains mostly correspondence mailed to Anne Tyler by friends, publishers, fans, etc. Some frequent correspondents include: Judith Jones, Tyler's editor at Alfred A. Knopf publishing house; Timothy Seldes, Tyler's literary agent at Russell & Volkening, Inc.; and Stuart Wright, publisher. One folder in this series is restricted.
  Processing note: undated items were foldered behind the previous dated item, as most correspondence materials were in rough chronological order when processed. Additionally, some correspondence was paper clipped together. In cases where the paper clipped materials were not of the same year, the bundles were usually moved to a specific folder named for the sender.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Access Restrictions: One folder of correspondence in Box 15 is closed to use.
  - 1964-1970 and undated (Box 13)
  - 1974-1981 (Box 13)
  - 1982 (Box 14)
  - 1983 (Box 14)
  - 1984 (Box 14)
  - 1985 (Box 14)
  - 1986-1987 (Box 14)
  - 1988 (Box 14)
  - Restricted correspondence (Box 15)
  - 1989 (Box 15)
  - 1990 (Box 15)
  - 1991 (Box 15)
  - 1992-1993 (Box 15)
  - 1994 (Box 15)
  - 1995 (Box 15)
  - 1996-1999 (Box 15)
  - Bill Henderson, Writer's Choice (Box 15)
  - Christine Newman (Box 15)
  - Donna Phillips, PEN Syndicated Fiction Project (Box 15)
  - Shannon Ravenel (Box 15)
  - Stephen Schlesinger (Box 15)
  - Phyllis Tyler (Box 15)
- Printed Materials, 1964-2005, 8.5 boxes
  This series contains a wide variety of materials related to Tyler and her writings. A substantial portion of this series is comprised of clippings from newspapers and magazines. Many of the clippings were clipped by Durrant's, an international clipping service. The Book Reviews, Excerpts, and Publicity materials are subdivided by book, and arranged in the order that the books were published.
  Oversize jacket art and publicity materials can be found in the Miscellaneous & Oversize Materials series.
  The "About" folder includes clippings of articles about Anne Tyler herself rather than about and individual book. The "Adaptations - The Accidental Tourist" folders include the movie's shooting schedule, production information, and newspaper clippings. The "Mentions" folder includes clippings of articles, etc., which make reference to Anne Tyler, her works, adaptations, etc.
  Additional book jackets/jacket art and publicity materials can be found in the Miscellaneous & Oversize Materials series.
  - About, 4 folders (Box 16)
  - Adaptations
    - The Accidental Tourist, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Adaptations (Box 17)
    - The Accidental Tourist script (Box 17)
    - Back When We Were Grownups, Earthly Possessions, Saint Maybe, A Slipping-Down Life (Box 17)
    - Breathing Lessons (film) (Box 17)
    - Breathing Lessons (play) (Box 17)
    - Earthly Possessions (play) (Box 17)
  - Awards and Recognition (Box 17)
  - Book jackets/jacket art, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Book Reviews (Box 18)
    - If Morning Ever Comes (Box 18)
    - The Tin Can Tree (Box 18)
    - A Slipping-Down Life (Box 18)
    - The Clock Winder (Box 18)
    - Celestial Navigation (Box 18)
    - Searching for Caleb (Box 18)
    - Earthly Possessions (Box 18)
    - Morgan's Passing (Box 18)
    - Dinner at the Homesick Restaurant (Box 18)
  - Book Reviews (Box 19)
    - Best American Short Stories (Box 19)
    - The Accidental Tourist, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Breathing Lessons, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Saint Maybe, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Book Reviews (Box 20)
    - Ladder of Years (Box 20)
    - Tumble Tower (Box 20)
    - A Patchwork Planet (Box 20)
    - Back When We Were Grownups (Box 20)
    - The Amateur Marriage (Box 20)
    - Best of the South, second volume (Box 20)
    - Digging to America (Box 20)
  - Excerpts (Box 21)
    - Earthly Possessions (Box 21)
    - Ladder of Years (Per Puro Caso) (Box 21)
    - The Amateur Marriage (Box 21)
    - Digging to America (Box 21)
  - Mentions (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous Foreign Language Materials, 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Publicity
    - If Morning Ever Comes and The Tin Can Tree (Box 21)
    - A Slipping-Down Life (Box 21)
    - The Clock Winder (Box 21)
    - Celestial Navigation (Box 21)
    - Searching for Caleb (Box 21)
    - Earthly Possessions (Box 21)
    - Morgan's Passing (Box 21)
  - Publicity (Box 22)
    - Dinner at the Homesick Restaurant (Box 22)
    - The Accidental Tourist (Box 22)
    - Breathing Lessons (Box 22)
    - Louder Than Words (Box 22)
    - Saint Maybe (Box 22)
    - Tumble Tower (Box 22)
    - Ladder of Years, first of 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Publicity (Box 23)
    - Ladder of Years, second of 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Best of the South (Box 23)
    - A Patchwork Planet (Box 23)
    - Back When We Were Grownups (Box 23)
    - The Amateur Marriage and Digging to America (Box 23)
    - Timothy Tugbottom Says No! (Box 23)
  - Scholarship, first and second of 3 folders (Box 23)
  - Scholarship, third of 3 folders (Box 24)
  - Scholarship and Saint Maybe Excerpt (Box 24)
  - Speaking Engagement: Eudora Welty and Anne Tyler at Duke University, 1982 (Box 24)
- Miscellaneous & Oversize Materials, 1963-2005, 1.5 boxes
  Miscellaneous items include mostly printed materials. Some are publicity items or clippings that related to multiple books, others refer to speakers or symposiums about Tyler's work. Also included is a handwritten writing assignment.
  Oversize materials are housed in Oversize Box 25. These materials relate to the Writings and Printed Materials series.
  - Miscellaneous items (Box 24)
  - Note from Cyril Clemens (Box 24)
  - Other Writings (oversize) (Box 25)
  - Book Jackets/Jacket Art (oversize) (Box 25)
  - Publicity (oversize) (Box 25)